Herbert Bain Knowles Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Herbert Bain Knowles Papers 1941-1945
MSS12112
Knowles, Herbert Bain, 1894-1976
400 items
5 containers plus 1 oversize
2 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Naval officer. Correspondence, orders to duty, subject files concerning invasion plans and occupation reports for Guam, Japan, Kwajalein Islands (Marshall Islands), Leyte Island (Philippines), Lingayen (Luzon, Philippines), Okinawa Island (Japan), Saipan (Northern Mariana Islands), and Tarawa Atoll (Kiribati), and printed matter relating to Knowles's service with the Amphibious Forces in the Pacific during World War II.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Forrestal, James, 1892-1949--Correspondence.; Kauffman, James Laurence, 1887-1963--Correspondence.; Knowles, Herbert Bain, 1894-1976.; Stone, George Roben, 1909-1943--Correspondence.
Organizations
United States. Navy.
Subjects
World War, 1939-1945--Amphibious operations.; World War, 1939-1945--Guam.; World War, 1939-1945--Japan.; World War, 1939-1945--Kiribati.; World War, 1939-1945--Marshall Islands.; World War, 1939-1945--Naval operations, American.; World War, 1939-1945--Northern Mariana Islands.; World War, 1939-1945--Pacific Ocean.; World War, 1939-1945--Philippines.
Places
Kwajalein Island (Marshall Islands)--History.; Leyte Island (Philippines)--History.; Lingayen (Philippines)--History.; Okinawa Island (Japan)--History.; Saipan--History.; Tarawa Atoll (Kiribati)--History.; United States--History, Naval.
Occupations
Naval officers.
Provenance
The papers of Herbert Bain Knowles, naval officer, were deposited in the Library of Congress by the Naval Historical Foundation in 1968 and converted to gift in 1998.
Additional Guides
In 1983 the Library published William Frederick Halsey, Jr., Ernest Joseph King, and Herbert Bain Knowles: Registers of Their Papers in the Library of Congress.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Herbert Bain Knowles are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1894, Mar. 20 Born, North Newburg, Maine
1913 1917 Student, United States Naval Academy, Annapolis, Md.
1917 Commissioned ensign
1919 Married Helen Kamp
1920 1926 Duty in USS Arkansas and submarine service
1922 First command, submarine USS S-9
1928 1940 Served in submarines, on surface vessels, with Bureau of Engineers, and as District operations officer, Fourteenth Naval District
1941 Commander, USS Heywood
1942 Promoted to captain
1943 1945 Commanded Transport Division 18, Transport Squadron 12, and Transport Division 34
1945 1946 Assistant chief of staff for operations, First Naval District, Boston, Mass.
1947 Promoted to rear admiral Retired
1976, Mar. 3 Died, Portland, Maine
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Herbert Bain Knowles (1894-1976) cover the years 1941-1945 and describe Knowles’s service in the United States Navy’s amphibious forces in the Pacific during World War II. The collection traces the American advance across the Pacific Ocean to Japan via the Solomon Islands, Attu, Kiska, Tarawa, Kawajalein, Saipan, Guam, Leyte, Lingayen, and Nagasaki, Japan, during 1942-1945.
Included are mimeographs and carbon copies of after action reports of Knowles and others, conference notes, service communications, operation plans and orders for assault landings and training exercises, marine division field reports, Knowles’s unpublished “History of U.S.S. Heywood,” and his war diaries or monthly logs of Transport Division 18 and Transport Squadron 12. Also included are photographs of the Leyte beachhead and a military intelligence bulletin. Personal materials consist of a few items of correspondence, health reports, orders, response to orders, vouchers, and similar documents depicting Knowles’s naval life while not in combat or engaged in ship and troop deployment.
Knowles was a pioneer and innovator in the art of assault troop landings. His ideas and innovations, as found in his operational plans and orders and in his after action reports, were to become widely adopted for amphibious landings by United States forces.
Arrangement of the Papers
The collection is organized by topic or type of material.
Container List
- Personal file, 1941-1945, (4 folders) (Box 1)
- Writings, “History of U.S.S. Heywood ,” undated (Box 1)
- Military file (Box 1)
  - War diaries (Box 1)
    - Transport Division 18, 1943-1944 1943-1944 (Box 1)
    - Transport Squadron 12, 1944-1945 (Box 1)
  - Campaigns (Box 1)
    - Solomon Islands (Box 1)
    - After action reports and operation order, July-Aug. 1942, (3 folders) (Box 1)
    - Attu and Kiska, communication plans and instructions, operation orders, reports, Apr. 1942-[Aug.] 1943, (11 folders) (Box 1)
    - Kiska, field order, operation plans, operation order, Aug. 1943, (7 folders) (Box 2)
    - Tarawa, Makin, and Apamama (Box 2)
      - Boat pools, [Oct.] 1943 (Box 2)
      - After action reports, operation orders, operation plans, planning conference notes, Oct.-Dec. 1943, (11 folders) (Box 2)
    - Kawajalein, landing attack order and report on capture, Jan.-Feb. 1944, (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Saipan, after action report, landing attack order, casualty memorandum cover, May-July 1944, (3 folders) (Box 3)
    - Guam, after action report, landing attack order, list of vessels, July-Aug. 1944, (3 folders) (Box 3)
    - Leyte, after action reports, landing attack order, photographs, training memorandum, Aug.-Oct. 1944, undated, (6 folders) (Box 3)
    - Lingayen, after action reports, assault bombardment, field training memorandum and report, landing attack orders, operation order, planning conference notes, transport schedules, Nov. 1944-Feb. 1945, (11 folders) (Box 4)
    - Okinawa, after action reports, landing attack order, landing craft losses, periodic reports, Mar.-Apr. 1945, (5 folders) (Box 4)
    - Nagasaki, after action report, landing plans, July-Sept. 1945, (3 folders) (Box 4)
  - Battle problems, communications, Nov. 1944-Mar. 1945, (2 folders) (Box 4)
  - Communications, daily schedules, staff memorandums, and memorandums and instructions on various subjects, Dec. 1944-May 1945, undated, (5 folders) (Box 4)
  - Efate naval base, defenses, gunnery practice, Nov. 1943, (3 folders) (Box 4)
  - Hawaii, amphibious training, training exercises, Sept.-Oct. 1943 (Box 4)
  - Wellington, New Zealand, amphibious training, aircraft codes, field training, messages, orders, training reports, Sept.-Oct. 1943, undated, (7 folders) (Box 4)
- Printed matter, Intelligence Bulletin, Apr. 1945 (Box 5)
- Oversize maps, plans, and drawings (Box OV 1)